Melyssa Minto

PhD Candidate in Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

Personal Info

E-mail

melyssa.minto@duke.edu

WWW

melyssaminto.com

Twitter

@MelyssaMinto

Soft Skills

Leadership	
Communication	
Logistical	
Creativity	
Mentorship	
Project Management	••••

Hard Skills

R	
Python	
Bash/Shell	
MATLAB	
HTML	
CSS	
Java	
Markdown	
Git	
SLURM	
HTML Scrubbing	
Data Cleaning	
Bayesian Stats	
Grant Writing	

Language

Spanish



Objective

2020

My research interests lie at the intersection of computational biology, epigenomics, and human health. Longterm, my goal is to study epigenomics in the context of health disparities and to make findings in this field more accessible especially to marginalized populations. To achieve this goal, I enrolled in the Computational Biology and Bioinformatics PhD program at Duke University and joined Anne West's lab where I am developing the statistical and computational skills to work with (epi)genomic data. Thanks to large-scale sequencing projects, there exists a plethora of genomic and epigenomic data; however the field needs integrative approaches to finding relevant biological information within these data. During my PhD, I am building statistical models to elucidate transcription factor binding patterns that regulate the maturation of cerebellar granule neurons, thus advancing understanding of brain development. This training will equip me to be a leader in epigenomics, and with the resources and training of the HHMI Gilliam Fellowship, I look forward to collaborating with like-minded scientists to both advance knowledge and to tear down systemic barriers in STEM.

Education and Certificates

Current	Ph.D. in Computational Biology and Bioinformatics Duke University
July 2018	Cert in Integrative Genomics Summer Institute for Statistical Genetics
July 2018	Cert in MCMC for Statistical Genetics Summer Institute for Statistical Genetics
May 2017	B.S. in Mathematics and B.S. in Biology, Meredith College, Raleigh, NC

Project Manager | Duke Data+ Environmental Public Health Tracking

Leadership and Involvement

Troject Manager Bake Baka Environmentar abite Health Macking
Mentor Durham Public School Women in Math Program
President Triangle Science Share
Graduate Student Q&A YouTube Live Duke Graduate School
Seminar Planning Committee Computational Biology & Bioinformatics
Alumni Networking Panel & Reception Committee Bouchet Society
Few-Glasson Alumni Society Selection Committee Duke Graduate School
Faculty Mentor Award Selection Committee Duke Graduate School
Dean's Awards Selection Committee Duke Graduate School
Gordon G. Hammes Teaching Selection Committee Duke Graduate School
Retreat Planning Committee Computational Biology & Bioinformatics
Graduate Student Welcome Panel Duke Graduate School

Honors and Awards

2017 - Current	Duke BioCoRE Scholar
2017	Deborah K. Smith Award for Achievement in Biology Meredith College
2017	Ford Foundation Fellowship Honorable Mention
2016	Who's Who Among Students in American Universities and Colleges
2016	Beta Beta National Biological Honor Society
2016	Pi Mu Epsilon National Mathematics Honor Society
2016	Outstanding Student Researcher of the Year NC Central University

Teaching Experience	
August 2018/ August 2019	Data Carpentries Teacher's Assistant Assisted during a Bootcamp for a University program for genomics and genetics at Duke University. This Bootcamp included curriculum that covered Unix command line, programming in python using jupyter, data and project organization, and version control with Git.

2017 - Current Tech Assistant/Instructor, Black Girls Code

Volunteer to help organize, set up, and teach girls ages 7-17 about the basic principles behind coding, computer science, and engineering. Serve as a role model for girls by sharing my expertise and relevant experience.

development of cerebellum | IRTG Dissecting and Reengineering the Regulatory

Seminar/Conference Presentations

Sep 2020	Zic regulates cerebellar granule neuron maturation in late developmental stages through noncanonical binding Cold Spring Harbor Labs - Epigenetics and Chromatin
Sep 2019	Computational methods to model the dynamic binding of the Zic Transcription
	Factor in Postnatal Development of the Cerebellum Duke Neurobiology Retreat
	and Duke Computational Biology and Bioinformatics Retreat
April 2019	Bioinformatic analysis of H3K27me3 and H3K27ac dynamics of postnatal

Genome February 2017 Cray Cray Morphometrics: Advancing Morphometric Delimitation of Species of Crayfish | Shaw University Research Symposium

November 2016 Cleaning Electronic Medical Records Using Novel R Package Monolnc | Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minority Students

May 2016 Monoinc: An R Package | North Carolina Central University

May 2016 A Study of the Risks of Teenage Pregnancy in the U.S. | Meredith College Celebrating Student Achievement Day (CSA Day)

Research Experience

DISSERTATION RESEARCH

My current research involves an integrative approach to determine regulators or psychostimulant induced genomic changes in Parvalbumin (PV) Interneurons as well as transcriptional regulators of maturation in Cerebellar Granule Neurons (CGNs) in Dr. Anne West's Lab. Since research from the lab has already shown that PV cells are integral in forming addictive like behaviors, understanding the genomic regulation that occurs in these cells will reveal insights as to how addiction is formed on a biological level and novel targets to treat addiction. As for my primary project, looking at how genome regulation changes throughout maturity in a post mitotic cell population opens the door to understanding how transcription factors and the 3D genome play a role driving cell maturation. I will be developing a Bayesian graphical model to learn the variation of TF binding throughout a time course such that it will reveal how TFs are changing their binding patterns over time. This will have mechanistic implications outside of CGNs.

INDUSTRY EXPERIENCE

JANUARY 2017 – August 2017 | ScitoVation | Efficiently balanced multiple projects from within and outside of the computational toxicology team manner to meet each quarterly deadline. Projects included curating chemical-assay plate data, performing gene expression/enrichment analysis, creating a pipeline to perform a systematic literature search with the goal of curating publicly available data on a compound's bioactivity. Each project was clearly documented, and version controlled.

UNDERGRADUATTE RESEARCH

June 2016 | Prairie Ridge Ecostation, North Carolina Museum of Natural Sciences | Collected data from both the NC Museum of Natural Sciences and the Smithsonian, used morphometric and genotype data to delimit crayfish species. Incorporated machine learning algorithms to automate morphometric analysis and aid in identification of characteristics that can be used to distinguish crayfishes.

June 2016 – August 2016 | **ENBISYS Lab, North Carolina State University** | Found gene targets to upregulate the synthesis of lignin, a biofuel, by differential analysis in R. These findings were used to further develop a computational model based on the lignin biosynthesis pathway to better understand how to increase the production of biofuels.

June 2015 – Dec 2016 | Biomedical/Biotechnology Research Institute, North Carolina Central University | Served as a lead statistician on a dynamic team for a research project analyzing growth data, epigenetic data, and genetic data. Created R package, Monolnc, to clean longitudinal dat – It flags data that is either outside of a range or non-monotonic and performs a single or weighted imputation. Helped to develop the study design and statistical methodology for a behavioral zebrafish study that modeled fetal alcohol syndrome.

May 2015 – May 2016 | Meredith College | The Implications Associated with the Perceptions of Farmwork and Agriculture Distributed a survey and used R to analyze the awareness of farmworkers among Meredith College community. Determined the steps to increase awareness the unfair conditions of farmworkers. A Study of the Risks of Teenage Pregnancy in the U.S. Conducted statistical analyses to identify risk factors for teenage pregnancy using data provided by the National Survey for Family Growth.

May 2014 – August 2014 | **DREAM STEM, North Carolina Central University** | Under the tutelage of Dr. Goalin – Milledge, analyzed the genetic risk for type-2 diabetes using various statistical tests conducted in R. This resulted in SNP targets for type-2 diabetes.

Publications

IN PREPARATION

1. David Gallegos, **Melyssa Minto**, Fang Liu, Aryanna Yousefzedeh, Mariah Hazlett, Greg Crawford, Anne E West. Psychostimulant-regulated transcriptional plasticity in Nucleus Accumbens fast-spiking interneurons. *In Preparation*

PUBLISHED

- Chantel I Nicolas, Kevin Bronson, Salil N Pendse, Alina Efremenko, Jeremy M Fitzpatrick, Melyssa S Minto, Kamel Mansouri, Miyoung Yoon, Martin B Phillips, Rebecca A Clewell, Melvin E Andersen, Harvey J Clewell III, Patrick D McMullen. The TTC Data Mart: an interactive browser for Threshold of Toxicological Concern calculations. Computational Toxicology. 2020
- 2. Patrick D. McMullen, Melvin E. Andersen, Brian Cholewa, Harvey J. Clewell, Katherine M. Dunnick, Jessica K. Hartman, Kamel Mansouri, Melyssa S. Minto, Chantel I. Nicolas, Martin B. Phillips, Scott Slattery, Miyoung Yoon, Rebecca A. Clewell, Evaluating opportunities for advancing the use of alternative methods in risk assessment through the development of fit-for-purpose in vitro assays. Toxicology in Vitro (48).2018
- 3. **Melyssa Minto**, Michele Josey, Clarlynda Williams-DeVane. *Monotonic Increasing*. (2016). R package version 1.1. https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=MonoInc